Hello, and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today
we're going to be learning how to
find percent composition by mass.
Which, the whole entire idea behind
this is, this is something that
allows chemists to find the amount of
an element within a given compound.
So it allows us to be able to figure
out essentially how pure a substance is.
Now the way that we're going to
look at this with percents is just
like any other mathematical steps.
is that a percent is the part over the
whole, or more specifically, we're going
to be assuming that we have a hundred gram
sample and trying to figure out, well,
how much of it is within that sample.
So let's take a whole look at this.
So what we're going to be
using is the following formula.
So what this is, is the mass percent
is the total of a given element.
So how much of that mass there is.
using the molar mass and then
dividing that by the molar mass
of the compound times 100%.
So this is a formula that we're going
to be using throughout this entire
video, going through multiple different
examples of how you can calculate
percent composition and how you
can figure out how much of a sample
you have with a given mass as well.
So we're going to go through
several different examples.
And let's try to take a look
at three easy steps for how we
can do these types of problems.
So with empirical formulas, the
great thing about it is that there's
three simple steps for how to do
every single one of these problems.
The first thing you're going to do
is find the total molar mass of each
element within the given compound.
meaning that we have to count
the number of atoms of each type.
So if there's two carbons, we got
to make sure we multiply our molar
mass of carbon by two, for example.
Our second step is we need to
find the molar mass of the entire,
the entire compound as a whole.
Um, being that that is going to
be the denominator of our formula.
Last step is you just plug it
all in into your formula and that
is what we're going to be doing
in all these different examples.
Let's go into an example that we can
do together and as you're going through
these, please feel free to try to
pause it and try to do them on your
own to see if you can do them as well.
Okay, let's do the following problem.
So it says, calculate the
percent composition by mass
of C and O in CO2, which more
specifically is carbon and oxygen.
So let's go through it.
Well, our first step was for us to be
able to calculate the amount of molar
mass for each element within the compound.
So the first thing you're going
to have to do is look up the molar
masses from the periodic table,
which I did for us for this problem.
So if we have our compound, which in this
case is CO2, What we have to do is count
the number of each atom to calculate
what the total Mass is for each element.
So for example in CO2 I have one
carbon atom So what I'm going to do is
multiply that one by a smaller mass.
So if I do one times 12.
01 grams per mole, I'm going to get 12.
01 grams per mole.
Now, for oxygen, right, what are we
going to do for the other portion?
Well, with oxygen, we need
to count both atoms, right?
We have two atoms of oxygen.
So we'll take 2 times 15.
99 grams per mole and that's going
to be, that's going to equal 31.
98 grams per mole.
So that is for the first part.
Now for the second step, what we're
going to do is we're going to take those
values Um, and add them up to find what
the total molar mass is of our compound.
So if we add up both, both
these values here, we're going
to get up our molecular mass.
So our molar mass for the compound, the
molar mass of CO2 is going to be 12.
01.
Plus 31.
98 grams per mole, and what
we will get in the end is 43.
99 grams per mole, or CO2.
Now our third step is just
taking all those values and
plugging them into our formula.
So let's first do for the
first one, which was carbon.
Okay, so with carbon, we had a value of,
uh, So let's write down our elements.
We have carbon, and we have oxygen.
So carbon had 12.
01 grams per mole in CO2,
and all that was over 43.
99 grams per mole.
Now what we will do is we're going
to multiply this by 100 percent
in order to get our percentage
of carbon within our sample.
So when we do our math here,
what we are going to get is 27.
32%.
of carbon.
Now for oxygen, we're going to
be doing the same general thing.
And keep in mind all of these
different elements that you
have, the total should equal 100.
So there's always a way for
you to double check as well.
So when we do the math
here, we should get 31.
98 grams per mole, right?
Which was the part of carbon.
over the whole, which is the 43.
99 grams per mole, what we got
in part two, times 100, and
what we are going to get is 72.
68%.
for our final answer.
So when we see CO2.
32 percent makes up carbon and 72.
68 percent makes up oxygen.
Let's try to do another
example just like this one.
For the second example, what we have
is ammonium nitrate, which is NH4NO3.
And this is used as a fertilizer
to add nitrogen to soil.
And what it asks you to do is
calculate the percent composition by
mass of N, H, and O of the compound.
So, exactly what do we need to do?
Well, if you remember, our very
first step is to find the total
molecular, molar mass of each element.
So, here I have on our, I have our little
handy dandy periodic table, um, just
with each element already found for us.
So we need to count every single
element that exists in a species.
Let's first start with nitrogen.
So nitrogen, when we look at the formula
for this particular element, we see that
we have two nitrogens in the compound.
There's one, and then there's two.
So with these kind of compounds,
we need to make sure we count
every single element in order to
make sure we count it correctly.
So if there are two of them, what we
are going to do is take two times, its
molecular mass, which is 4.01 grams
per mole, and that that total is gonna
be 28.02 grams per mole for nitrogen.
Now, we gotta do the same thing
for oxygen, so being that we have
3 atoms of oxygen in this formula,
so we have oxygen, and we have 3 of
them, that's gonna be 3 times 15.
99 grams per mole, and
that's going to equal 47.
97 grams per mole.
Now when we go through this again,
right, we can, we now count how many
hydrogens there are this time, and
we can see that there's a total of.
4 hydrogens that are within this
formula, so we'll have to take
that number 4, times it by 1.
008.
So, now that will give us the
masses for each individual part,
which will help us feed into how
much of each percent do we have.
So it'd be 4 times 1.008, which is 4.
032 total grams per mole for this species.
Now the good thing is about this
is by counting all these elements,
this allows us to figure out exactly
what the total molar mass is of the
entire element, because what we're
going to do is we're going to take
all these values that we have here
and we're going to add them all up.
So we'll take that 28.
02 plus the 47.
97.
Plus the 4.
032, and what we're going to get
is the total molar mass here, okay?
So when, now when we do that,
we'll get a total mass of 80.02
grams per mole, or NH4NO3.
Okay, so that is the total molar mass.
What is step three?
Well, step three is taking
these individual values and
plugging them into our formula.
So let's do that for ourselves.
So let's blow up that formula so we can
make it a little bit bigger so we can
remember exactly what we have to do.
So, we need to take the total mass
of each individual element, so
let's first start with nitrogen.
So nitrogen had 28.
02 as its value, so 28.
02 grams per mole, and let's move
that over just a little bit, and what
we are going to do is we're going to
divide that by the total, which was 80.
02,
and the whole thing is going
to be multiplied by 100 in
order to make it as a percent.
Now when we go through
that, we should get 35.
02 percent for nitrogen.
Now for oxygen, we're going to be
doing the exact same steps, right?
We take our partial, our
partial mass, which is the 47.
97 we see up there in red
all the way at the top.
So we'll take that 47.
97 grams per mole, and we're
going to divide that by our 80.
02 grams per mole.
And we'll times that by 100%, and
I'll put that on the left there just
to kind of show the whole thing.
And what we're going to see is
oxygen is the biggest portion
of this, and we will get 59.
95%, okay, for that.
Now let's also shove in hydrogen in here
somewhere, so hydrogen we'll do as the
last step, and that has a part of 4.
032 grams per mole, which is all the
way on the top right of your screen, and
we are going to divide that by that 80.
02 grams per mole, times 100.
Okay, now, when we get that last
percent, what we're going to get is 5.
03%.
Now to kind of make sure that when
you, before you turn in any of your
work to a teacher for assignment, you
kind of highlight or box them to show
every single one of those percent.
So we use the same
formula for each percent.
Let's go on to our next problem
to show another example of this,
and that'll be our last one.
Okay, so the following problem,
in our last example, it says The
formula for rust is F E 2 0 3.
How many grams of iron
are in 22.8 grams of rust?
So this one's a little bit of a little
bit of a stoichiometry problem, but this
is something that will help you figure
out how to use empirical formulas.
So we only need to find how much the mass
percent is of iron in this case, right?
So what is that mass percent?
So let's go through it with our
first step, right, which is find the
total molar mass of each element,
which we have the molar masses here.
We only are interested in iron, but we
still need to do both pieces to find what
the total molar masses, which is step two.
Our very first part is being that we
have two iron molecules, so we have
two of them 'cause of our subscript.
I mentioned that means that we have Fe2O3.
We're gonna take that two
times 55.85 grams per mole.
And we are going to get, um,
when we do that math, it's 111.
7 grams per mole of iron.
Now the second part is oxygen, and we
have a subscript of 3 in this compound.
So we have 3 times 15.
99 grams per mole, and we are
going to get a value of 47.
97 grams per mole for
our answer for that part.
Okay, now step two, we got to find the
molar mass of the whole entire compound,
meaning that we have to add up both
of the values that we just calculated.
So we got to add up the 111.
7 plus 47.97.
So let's rewrite that.
So it's 111.
7 grams per mole plus 47.
97 grams per mole.
Now, when we do that math, what we
are going to end up getting is 159.
67 grams per mole of
Fe2O3 of our species here.
So that is your total molar mass.
Now the last step is to find the percents.
Now, which two values do we need?
Well, we are interested in
iron in this particular one.
So when we go through our last and final
step here in order to find the portion
of iron, let that value before was 111.
7.
So we'll take that 111.
7 grams per mole of
iron, which is our part.
And we're going to divide that by the 159.
67 grams per mole of Fe2O3,
times that by 100 percent.
And what we are going to get is 69.
96 percent of, of iron in this sample.
How does that apply to a mass sample?
Well what that allows you to do, this
is a conversion term that we can use
to be able to figure out, okay, how
much iron is there in a given sample?
So let's take a look.
What was the original value?
So we were given that we had 22.
8 grams of rust.
that we collected in our sample.
So let's go back down here and try
to see exactly how can we use that.
So we have 22.
8 grams of Fe2O3.
Now a percent is the same thing as
saying out of 100, right, for every 100.
So the way that we can use
this thing to our advantage is
saying that, okay, I have 69.
96 grams of iron all over 100 grams
of Fe2O3, right, per cent out of 100.
So this is a conversion
term that you can use.
to cancel out grams.
Now you can also simply just
multiply the sample by the decimal
value too, which is that 0.
6996, you'd get the same answer.
But it's good to be able to see
how this works as a dimensional
analysis or a stoichiometry problem,
being that you always have to
show your work in all classes.
So when you do this right, you multiply
what's on top, and then divide what
is on the bottom, and you will get 15.
95 grams.
of iron are in this sample.
So this would be your final
answer for the problem.
So you can use these different
mass conversion or these mass
compositions for different purposes.
So I hope that this video to help so that
way you can see how to calculate these
to be able to solve these on homework.
Now for most of you, this is
for all chemistry students.
This is usually the, one of the most
common types of exam questions that
you see on exam one or exam two.
In most general chemistry and
introductory chemistry classes.
So make sure you're familiar with
them and check out my follow up video.
This on how to calculate an
empirical formula using the percents.
Okay, and I hope to see you all next time.
Thank you so much for stopping by.
Please hit that like and subscribe
button and please comment below.
If there's different videos
you'd like to see in the future.
All right.
Bye now.